Timber Cove Recreation Association Records
University of Houston-Clear Lake Archives & Special Collections
Timber Cove Recreation Association Records
1962-2006
Timber Cove Recreation Association
2011-0010
1.5 linear feet
University of Houston-Clear Lake Archives & Special Collections
Timber Cove Recreation Association Records covers the association's annual reports, minutes, budgets, membership, and items related to pool construction and maintenance from 1962 to 2006.
Administrative History
The Timber Cove neighborhood was developed in February 1958 on farmland previously owned by the Ballentine family. When NASA announced the construction of the Manned Spacecraft Center in this part of Harris County, astronauts and other NASA families purchased lots and homes in the neighborhood, creating a housing boom. The community developed into a close family-oriented neighborhood.
In 1962, the Timber Cove Civic Club formed an independent committee to investigate the feasibility of constructing a swimming pool and recreation area. After an initial survey of residents found over 70% favored the project, they held a charter membership drive to raise funds. Charter members paid a $50 initiation fee, $135 charter membership share and $65 annual dues. Membership surpassed the required minimum quota of 80 initial members by March 1963.
The Timber Cove Recreation Association incorporated on April 10, 1963 as a non-profit corporation to promote the public health and interests of the Timber Cove residents by owning and operating a swimming pool and clubhouse for its members. Taylor Lake Development Company deeded the land to the Timber Cove Recreation Association for $10 on April 22, 1963. TCRA contracted Abernathy Company to construct the swimming pool in May 1963. Traditional Homes built the clubhouse.
The swimming pool was purposefully designed to resemble the shape of the Mercury capsule to honor Timber Cove resident Col. John Glenn, the first American astronaut to orbit the Earth. The pool opened on June 22, 1963 with Opening Day celebrations on July 4, 1963.
Scope and Contents of the Records
Materials document the Timber Cove Recreation Association including annual reports, minutes, budgets, membership, and items related to pool construction and maintenance. Records were originally filed in chronological order by calendar year.
Arrangement
The records are arranged into six series:
Series I: Organizational File
Series II: Minutes
Series III: Financial Records
Series IV: Swimming Pool
Series V: Subject Files
Series VI: Plaque
Access Restrictions
Unrestricted
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Garrison, Arthur E.; Crawford, William S. Jr.; Isles, Roy; Markley, O. W.; Roze, Janet
Subjects (Organizations)
Abernathy Company; Taylor Lake Development Company; Timber Cove Dolphins (swim team); Timber Cove Recreation Association
Places
Timber Cove (Calif.); Lake Country Estates
Acquisition Information
Donated by Sheryl Kuhfeldt on behalf of TCRA. Materials brought to Archives by Dr. Deborah Griffin. TCRA retained copies of important original materials.
Related Material
See also the founding Timber Cove Collection #2011-0008 and Timber Cove Garden Club Records, #2011-0009.
Separated Material
Signed board of director election ballots, lifeguard applications with personal information, and pool incident reports were returned to the TCRA.
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Series I: Organizational Files
  - By-Laws -- Timber Cove Recreation Association, Inc, 1963; 1975 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Certificate and Articles of Incorporation of Timber Cove Recreation Association, Inc., April 1963 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Deed Taylor Lake Development Co. to Timber Cove Recreation Association, Inc., April 22, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Swimming Pool Contract and Building Permit, May-April 1963 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Introductory Notice to Residents, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Board of Directors Report (2nd floor addition), January 1966 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Release of Franchise Tax Lien, March 3, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Official Boundary Map and Assessors Map of the City of Taylor Lake Village, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Lake Country Estates Access to Pool, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Annual Reports, 1964; 1969,; 1984,; 1989,; 1991 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence to Members, 1965; 1983,; 1995,; 1997,; 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence from Members, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Membership, 1963; 1966,; 1968-1970,; 1982-1983,; 1992-1994,; 1997,; 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Maintenance Requests, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Newsletter, 1964-1969 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Oil, Gas, and Mineral Lease, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Emergency Plan, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Series II: Minutes
  - Minutes, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Minutes, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Minutes, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Minutes, 1971-1973 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Minutes, 1974-1980 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Minutes, 1981-1983; 1985 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Minutes, 1992-1994 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Minutes, 1995-1996; 1998 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Minutes, 2001-2003; 2006 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Series III: Financial Records
  - Taxes, 1964-1969; 1977 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Proposed Budget Review, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Finances, 1965; 1967 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Financial Records, 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Account Books, 1968-1970 (Box 2, Folder 7-9)
  - Treasurer's Reports, 1992-1997; 2001-2002 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Asset Age and Replacement Cost Analysis, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Receipts - Opening Day, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Receipts - Facilities Renovation, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Receipt - Roofing, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Series IV: Swimming Pool
  - Request for Bid, March 17, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Rules and Regulations, 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Maintenance and Operating Instructions, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Maintenance, 1992; 1994 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Agreement for Use, 1986; 1997 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Management Proposals, 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Pool Chemistry, Undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Troubleshooting, circa 1981 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Triton Sand Filters (Installation, Operation, & Service Manual), 1983 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - MSDS: Material Safety Data Sheet, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Chemical Usage (includes receipts), 1994-1997 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Pump, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Series V: Subject Files
  - Annual Information Packet, 1991-1994 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Annual Information Packet, 2000-2006 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Bulkhead Repair Proposals, 1993; 1995-1996 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Ice Machine, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Pest Control, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Spring Work Day, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Series VI: Plaque
  - Dolphins Swim Team, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 15)